<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Math and Data</title>
    <link>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Math and Data</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2017 22:37:44 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>the MIC Seminar</title>
      <link>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/micsem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2017 22:37:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/micsem/</guid>
      <description>The Mathematics, Information and Computation (MIC) Seminar runs at irregular intervals and covers specific aspects at the interface of applied maths, information theory and theory of computation.
Schedule Spring 17    Date &amp;amp; Time Speaker Title Room     Mar 21, 2:30pm Liza Rebrova (U Michigan) Local and global obstructions for the random matrix norm regularization CDS 650          Abstracts  Liza Rebrova: Local and Global obstructions for the random matrix norm regularization We study large n by n random matrices A with i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>reading</title>
      <link>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/news/reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 15:40:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/news/reading/</guid>
      <description>This week we are starting two weekly reading groups. One will study topics on high-dimensional Probability, whereas the other will focus on selected topics on Statistical Physics. You can check present and past reading groups in the corresponding page.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading Groups</title>
      <link>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 15:36:26 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/reading/</guid>
      <description> The Mad group hosts semester-long thematic reading groups. Publicly accessible here.
High Dimensional Probability Statistical Physics </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phd Program in the Mad group </title>
      <link>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/news/mediumarticle/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Dec 2016 11:01:01 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/news/mediumarticle/</guid>
      <description>Check out these articles if you are interested in applying to our PhD program!
 PhD in Data Science : The MaD Group
 PhD Application tips!
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to the Mad site!</title>
      <link>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/news/first/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 14:51:18 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/news/first/</guid>
      <description>The Mad (Math and Data) group was created in fall 2016 by Afonso Bandeira, Joan Bruna and Carlos Fernandez-Granda, three Assistant Professors at Courant Institute and the Center for Data Science.
We are always in the lookout for highly motivated students interested in understanding and developing the fundamental mathematical structures underpinning modern data analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Students and Visitors</title>
      <link>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/studentsvisitors/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 14:48:53 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/studentsvisitors/</guid>
      <description>Soledad Villar (jun 2017 - ) Moore-Sloan Research Fellow; optimization, probability, topology and data.
Augustin Cosse (oct 2016 - ) Postdoc; Tensor methods, inverse problems.
Alex Nowak (sep 2016 - may 2017 ) Visiting Student; deep learning, harmonic analysis.
Thomas Moreau (jan 2017 - mar 2017) Visiting Student; high-dimensional statistics, machine learning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Faculty</title>
      <link>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/faculty/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 14:48:45 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/faculty/</guid>
      <description>Core Afonso S. Bandeira Assistant Professor, Department of Mathematics and Center for Data Science.
Joan Bruna Assistant Professor, Department of Computer Science, Center for Data Science and Mathematics (affiliated).
Carlos Fernandez-Granda Assistant Professor, Department of Mathematics and Center for Data Science.
Affiliated Gerard Ben Arous Professor, Mathematics, Courant Institute.
Xi Chen Assistant Professor, IOMS, Stern School.
Sinan Gunturk Professor, Department of Mathematics, Courant Institute.
Eyal Lubetzky Associate Professor, Mathematics, Courant Institute.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>the MaD Seminar</title>
      <link>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 14:45:56 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/seminar/</guid>
      <description>The MaD seminar features leading specialists at the interface of Applied Mathematics, Statistics and Machine Learning.
Room: Auditorium Hall 150, Center for Data Science, NYU, 60 5th ave.
Time: 2:30pm-3:30pm, Reception will follow.
Subscribe to the Seminar Mailing list here
Schedule with Confirmed Speakers    Date Speaker Title     Sep 26 Yoram Singer (Princeton)    Sep 21 Esteban Tabak (NYU)    Sep 28 Laurent Demanet (MIT)    Oct 5 Dustin Mixon (Ohio State)    Oct 12 Lorenzo Rosasco (MIT)    Oct 19 Francis Bach (INRIA, ENS)    Oct 26 Rachel Ward (UT Austin)    Nov 2 Ivan Selesnick (NYU)    Nov 9 Mauro Maggioni (John Hopkins)    Nov 16 Emmanuel Abbe (Princeton)    Nov 23 THANKSGIVING    Nov 30 Guillermo Sapiro (Duke)    Dec 7 Alexandre d&amp;rsquo;Aspremont (ENS)     Schedule Spring 2017</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>the MaD Seminar Spring 2017</title>
      <link>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/seminar_spring2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 14:45:56 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/seminar_spring2017/</guid>
      <description>The MaD seminar features leading specialists at the interface of Applied Mathematics, Statistics and Machine Learning.
Room: Auditorium Hall 150, Center for Data Science, NYU, 60 5th ave.
Time: 2:30pm-3:30pm, Reception will follow.
Subscribe to the Seminar Mailing list here
Schedule with Confirmed Speakers    Date Speaker Title     Jan 26 Dave Donoho (Stanford) Optimal Shrinkage of Covariance Matrices in light of the spiked covariance model   Feb 2 Andrew Gelman (Columbia) Taking Bayesian Inference Seriously   Feb 9 Mar 20 May 11 Leslie Greengard (Courant) Inverse problems in acoustic scattering and cryo-electron microscopy   Feb 16 Ronald Coifman (Yale) Organization and Analysis on data tensors   Feb 23 John Wright (Columbia) Nonconvex Recovery of Low-Complexity Models   Mar 2 Gitta Kutyniok (TU Berlin) Optimal Approximation with Sparse Deep Neural Networks   Mar 9 Philippe Rigollet (MIT) Learning determinantal point processes   Mar 16 SPRING BREAK    Mar 23 Amit Singer (Princeton) PCA from noisy linearly transformed measurements   Mar 30 Stephane Mallat (ENS Ulm) Mathematial Mysteries of Deep Convolutional Networks   Apr 6 11am, 12 Waverly pl, L120 Ben Recht (UC Berkeley) Optimization Challenges in Deep Learning   Apr 13 Waheed Bajwa (Rutgers) Collaborative Dictionary Learning from Big, Distributed Data   Apr 20 Andrea Montanari (Stanford) The Landscape of some Statistical Learning Problems   Apr 27 Joel Tropp (Caltech) Sketchy Decisions: Low-rank matrix optimization with optimal storage   May 4 Thomas Strohmer (UC Davis) Murder, Matrices, and Minima - Adventures in Blind Deconvolution   May 11 4pm Leslie Greengard (Courant) Inverse problems in acoustic scattering and cryo-electron microscopy    Abstracts  Dave Donoho: Optimal Shrinkage of Covariance Matrices in light of the Spiked Covariance Model (joint work with Behrooz Ghorbani, Stanford)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 14:29:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mathsanddatanyu.github.io/website/about/</guid>
      <description>The Math and Data group is part of New York University&amp;rsquo;s Center for Data Science, and the Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences.
Its mission is to advance the Mathematical and Statistical foundations of Data Sciences, specializing in Signal processing and Inverse Problems, Machine Learning and Deep Learning, and High-dimensional statistics and Probability.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>