<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Golang on Math and Data</title>
    <link>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/tags/golang/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Golang on Math and Data</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2017 22:37:44 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/tags/golang/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>the MIC Seminar</title>
      <link>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/micsem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2017 22:37:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/micsem/</guid>
      <description>The Mathematics, Information and Computation (MIC) Seminar runs at irregular intervals and covers specific aspects at the interface of applied maths, information theory and theory of computation.
Schedule Fall 18 During the Fall the MIC Seminar will usually be in room 312 Tuesdays 6-7p.
   Date Speaker Title Room     Oct 16, 6p David Shirokoff (NJIT) Convex relaxations for variational problems arising from models of self-assembly WWH 312   Oct 23, 6p Didier Henrion (CNRS) Solving nonlinear PDEs with the Lasserre hierarchy WWH 312   Nov 2, 1:30p Anna Seigal (Berkeley) Structured Tensors and the Geometry of Data WWH 202   Nov 12, 12:15p Marylou Gabrie (ENS) Entropy and mutual information in models of deep neural networks CDS 650    Abstracts  Marylou Gabrie: Entropy and mutual information in models of deep neural networks The successes and the multitude of applications of deep learning methods have spurred efforts towards quantitative modeling of the performance of deep neural networks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>reading</title>
      <link>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/news/reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 15:40:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/news/reading/</guid>
      <description>This week we are starting two weekly reading groups. One will study topics on high-dimensional Probability, whereas the other will focus on selected topics on Statistical Physics. You can check present and past reading groups in the corresponding page.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading Groups</title>
      <link>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 15:36:26 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/reading/</guid>
      <description> The Mad group hosts semester-long thematic reading groups. Publicly accessible here.
Fall 2018 working group schedule High Dimensional Probability Statistical Physics </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phd Program in the Mad group </title>
      <link>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/news/mediumarticle/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Dec 2016 11:01:01 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/news/mediumarticle/</guid>
      <description>Check out these articles if you are interested in applying to our PhD program!
 PhD in Data Science : The MaD Group
 PhD Application tips!
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to the Mad site!</title>
      <link>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/news/first/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 14:51:18 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/news/first/</guid>
      <description>The Mad (Math and Data) group was created in fall 2016 by Afonso Bandeira, Joan Bruna and Carlos Fernandez-Granda, three Assistant Professors at Courant Institute and the Center for Data Science.
We are always in the lookout for highly motivated students interested in understanding and developing the fundamental mathematical structures underpinning modern data analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>People</title>
      <link>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/people/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 14:48:45 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/people/</guid>
      <description>Core faculty Afonso S. Bandeira Assistant Professor, Department of Mathematics and Center for Data Science. 
Joan Bruna Assistant Professor, Department of Computer Science, Center for Data Science and Mathematics (affiliated).
Carlos Fernandez-Granda Assistant Professor, Department of Mathematics and Center for Data Science.
Postdocs Shuyang Ling (Aug 2017 - ) Courant Instructor; compressive sensing, convex optimization, computational harmonic analysis
Soledad Villar (Jun 2017 - ) Moore-Sloan Research Fellow; optimization, probability, topology and data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>the MaD Seminar</title>
      <link>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 14:45:56 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/seminar/</guid>
      <description>The MaD seminar features leading specialists at the interface of Applied Mathematics, Statistics and Machine Learning. It is partly supported by the Moore-Sloan Data Science Environment at NYU.
Room: Auditorium Hall 150, Center for Data Science, NYU, 60 5th ave.
Time: 2:00pm-3:00pm, Reception will follow.
Subscribe to the Seminar Mailing list here
Schedule with Confirmed Speakers    Date Speaker Title     Sep 13 Nate Silver Forecasting the midterm elections   Sep 20 Ivan Selesnick (NYU Tandon) Sparse Regularization via Convex Analysis   Sep 27 Cristopher Moore (Santa Fe Institute) Statistical physics, statistical inference, and community detection in networks   Oct 4 Andrew Blumberg (UT Austin) Topological data analysis for scientific inference   Oct 11 Venkat Chandrasekaran (Caltech) Learning Regularizers from Data   Oct 18 Cathy O&amp;rsquo;Neil Big data, inequality, and democracy: what can mathematics offer?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>the MaD Seminar</title>
      <link>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/seminar_spring2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 14:45:56 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/seminar_spring2018/</guid>
      <description>The MaD seminar features leading specialists at the interface of Applied Mathematics, Statistics and Machine Learning. It is partly supported by the Moore-Sloan Data Science Environment at NYU.
Room: Auditorium Hall 150, Center for Data Science, NYU, 60 5th ave.
Time: 2:00pm-3:00pm, Reception will follow.
Subscribe to the Seminar Mailing list here
Note special time and location of the first talk by Sebastien Bubeck
Schedule with Confirmed Speakers    Date Speaker Title     Jan 30, 3:45pm-5:00pm, WWH 1302 Sebastien Bubeck (Microsoft Research) k-server and metrical task systems on trees   Feb 8 David Rothschild (Microsoft Research) Public Opinion during the 2020 election   Feb 15, 3-4pm, CDS 150 Rachel Ward (UT Austin) Autotuning the learning rate in stochastic gradient methods   Feb 22 Zhou Fan (Stanford) Eigenvalues in multivariate random effects models   Mar 1 Thomas Pock (TU Graz) Learning better models for computer vision   Mar 8 Amir Ali Ahmadi (Princeton) Polynomial Optimization and Dynamical Systems   Mar 15 SPRING BREAK    Mar 22 Mahdi Soltanolkotabi (USC) Learning via Nonconvex Optimization: ReLUs, neural nets and submodular maximization   Mar 29 Alejandro Ribeiro (UPenn) Convolutional Neural Networks Architectures for Signals Supported on Graphs   Apr 5 Justin Romberg (Georgia Tech) Solving Nonlinear Equations using Convex Programming   Apr 12 Wotao Yin (UCLA) Asynchronous Parallel Computing for Optimization   Apr 19 Anirvan Sengupta (Rutgers) Manifold Representation by an Unsupervised Neural Net: Biology, Mathematics and Computation   Apr 26 Ankur Moitra (MIT) Robustness Meets Algorithms   May 3 Rene Vidal (John Hopkins) Global Optimality in Matrix Factorization and Deep Learning    Schedule Fall 2017</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>the MaD Seminar Fall 2017</title>
      <link>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/seminar_fall2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 14:45:56 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/seminar_fall2017/</guid>
      <description>The MaD seminar features leading specialists at the interface of Applied Mathematics, Statistics and Machine Learning.
Room: Auditorium Hall 150, Center for Data Science, NYU, 60 5th ave.
Time: 2:00pm-3:00pm, Reception will follow.
Subscribe to the Seminar Mailing list here
Schedule with Confirmed Speakers    Date Speaker Title     Sep 14 Yoram Singer (Princeton) Adaptive Regularization   Sep 21 Esteban Tabak (NYU) Conditional Density Estimation through Optimal Transport   Sep 28 Laurent Demanet (MIT) Extrapolation from sparsity   Oct 5 Dustin Mixon (Ohio State) A semidefinite relaxation of k-means clustering   Oct 12 Lorenzo Rosasco (MIT) (un)conventional regularization for efficient large scale machine learning   Oct 19 Francis Bach (INRIA, ENS) Bridging the Gap between Constant Step Size Stochastic Gradient Descent and Markov Chains   Oct 26 Rachel Ward (UT Austin)    Nov 2 Ivan Selesnick (NYU)    Nov 9 Mauro Maggioni (John Hopkins) Multiscale Methods for Dictionary Learning, Regression, Measure Estimation and Optimal Transport for data near low-dimensional sets   Nov 16 Emmanuel Abbe (Princeton) Graph Powering: mixing Bayesian and spectral methods   Nov 23 THANKSGIVING    Nov 30 Guillermo Sapiro (Duke) Learning to Succeed while Teaching to Fail: Privacy in Machine Learning Systems   Dec 7 Alexandre d&amp;rsquo;Aspremont (ENS)     Abstracts  Yoram Singer: Adaptive Regularization We describe a framework for deriving and analyzing online optimization algorithms that incorporate adaptive, data dependent regularization, also termed preconditioning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>the MaD Seminar Spring 2017</title>
      <link>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/seminar_spring2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 14:45:56 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mad.cds.nyu.edu/seminar_spring2017/</guid>
      <description>The MaD seminar features leading specialists at the interface of Applied Mathematics, Statistics and Machine Learning.
Room: Auditorium Hall 150, Center for Data Science, NYU, 60 5th ave.
Time: 2:30pm-3:30pm, Reception will follow.
Subscribe to the Seminar Mailing list here
Schedule with Confirmed Speakers    Date Speaker Title     Jan 26 Dave Donoho (Stanford) Optimal Shrinkage of Covariance Matrices in light of the spiked covariance model   Feb 2 Andrew Gelman (Columbia) Taking Bayesian Inference Seriously   Feb 9 Mar 20 May 11 Leslie Greengard (Courant) Inverse problems in acoustic scattering and cryo-electron microscopy   Feb 16 Ronald Coifman (Yale) Organization and Analysis on data tensors   Feb 23 John Wright (Columbia) Nonconvex Recovery of Low-Complexity Models   Mar 2 Gitta Kutyniok (TU Berlin) Optimal Approximation with Sparse Deep Neural Networks   Mar 9 Philippe Rigollet (MIT) Learning determinantal point processes   Mar 16 SPRING BREAK    Mar 23 Amit Singer (Princeton) PCA from noisy linearly transformed measurements   Mar 30 Stephane Mallat (ENS Ulm) Mathematial Mysteries of Deep Convolutional Networks   Apr 6 11am, 12 Waverly pl, L120 Ben Recht (UC Berkeley) Optimization Challenges in Deep Learning   Apr 13 Waheed Bajwa (Rutgers) Collaborative Dictionary Learning from Big, Distributed Data   Apr 20 Andrea Montanari (Stanford) The Landscape of some Statistical Learning Problems   Apr 27 Joel Tropp (Caltech) Sketchy Decisions: Low-rank matrix optimization with optimal storage   May 4 Thomas Strohmer (UC Davis) Murder, Matrices, and Minima - Adventures in Blind Deconvolution   May 11 4pm Leslie Greengard (Courant) Inverse problems in acoustic scattering and cryo-electron microscopy    Abstracts  Dave Donoho: Optimal Shrinkage of Covariance Matrices in light of the Spiked Covariance Model (joint work with Behrooz Ghorbani, Stanford)</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>